<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons on these wordes of Peter the apostle, honour all men, loue brotherly felowship ... preached at Marlebrough the seuenth of Nouember, and fifth of Ianuarie 1595 / by Charles Pynner, minister of the Church of Wotton-Basset in Northwiltshire.</title>
            <author>Pinner, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23234197</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23234197</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09677)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1802:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons on these wordes of Peter the apostle, honour all men, loue brotherly felowship ... preached at Marlebrough the seuenth of Nouember, and fifth of Ianuarie 1595 / by Charles Pynner, minister of the Church of Wotton-Basset in Northwiltshire.</title>
                  <author>Pinner, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 93 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Creede,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1) B-F⁸ G³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through; page numbers defaced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, II, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS, on theſe wordes of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle:
<q>
                  <l>Honour all men:</l>
                  <l>Loue brotherly felowſhip,</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epiſt. 1. chap. 2. verſ. 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Preached at Marlebrough the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth of Nouember, and fifth of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie</hi> 1595. <hi>by</hi> Charles Pynner, Miniſter of the Church of Wot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Baſſet in North-wiltſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>VVhile we haue time, let vs do good vnto all men; but eſpecially vnto them, which are of the houſhold of faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Thomas Creede. 1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26420:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26420:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and my eſpeciall good Lady,</hi> Anne, <hi>Ladie</hi> de La VVarr, wife vnto the L. <hi>de La Warr</hi> that now is a grace, mercie, and peace, from God the Father, and from the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, when at the requeſt of my worſhipfull and godly friend, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Iohn Bailiffe,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Maior of <hi>Marl-brough,</hi> I had there preached theſe two Sermons; I purpoſed euen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though thwarted til now by ſome occaſions) to offer the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:26420:3"/>vnto your Ladiſhip, in part of pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a much greater ſumme, which for many your benefites (as manie knowe, and my ſelfe moſt willinglie acknowledge) is due vnto you. And the rather I haue done this, and in this kinde ſought ſome part of recompence, becauſe as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth vnto God, <hi>One day in thy Courts, is better then a thouſand:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.13.</note> So your whole life tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vnto others, and to mee eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that one Sermon, yea one ſentence of the Lawe of GOD, <hi>is dearer vnto you then thouſands of Gold and Siluer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.73</note> And therfore this ſpark of Gods grace, howe little ſo euer it be, (if any at al it be) I know wil be accepted of your Ladiſhip, and all other of like ſpirite: in which
<pb facs="tcp:26420:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>hope I haue beene bold to make it publike: deſiring it may worke that good in others, which the like labours of others by Gods grace, (and I humbly thanke him for this grace) in ſome meaſure hath wrought in mee. And I pray God this zealous care may ſtill be in vs, &amp; chiefly in thoſe that haue receiued moſt, to helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which eſpecially haue neede thereof, as lacking the liuelie voyce of theyr owne paſtours. In the want of which duetie in many moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (of whome, howe many, haue receiued how many tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which go not abroade, or ſo broade as they might?) euen he, which hath receiued a little (I ſpeake for my ſelfe) may, I truſt, bee allowed to
<pb facs="tcp:26420:4"/>giue a little. <hi>VVhich if there be a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling minde firſt</hi> (as ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus preſerue your good Ladyſhip, with my honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable good Lord, and your happy children (happie, if they knowe their happineſſe of ſuch their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:) and increaſe in you the graces of his holy ſpirite. Amen. From London the ſecond of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. 1597.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours bounden, and in all dutie to commaund:</hi> Charles Pynner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26420:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE FIRST Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. Pet. Chap. 2. Verſ. 17.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Honour all men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle in theſe words, not ſo much teacheth the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to whome hee writeth, as exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them vnto cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine duties, which it ſeemeth they knew before. Like as himſelfe in this, and his other Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, with the reſt of the Apoſtles, and indeede all the holy Scriptures, both of the old and new Teſtament, are very plentifull in this matter of exhorting. <hi>Theſe things commaunde
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26420:5"/>and teach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.11</note> faith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie,</hi> the firſt &amp; fourth. That which is taught muſt be commaunded: like as that which is commanded muſt firſt bee taught. Which ſheweth our dulnes (deerely beloued) and how reſtie we are, and needing a ſpurre in the knowen way.</p>
            <p>And yet it may bee, many <hi>Philips</hi> heere, not ſo vnwilling to embrace their dutie, as not knowing what dutie is, that they may embrace it. In the fourteenth of <hi>Iohn, If ye had knowen me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye ſhould haue knowne my father alſo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 14.7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>and from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ye know him, and haue ſeene him. Phillip</hi> ſaide vnto him, <hi>Lord, ſhewe vs the Father, and it ſufficeth.</hi> So we: ſhew vs what it is to honour all men, and we will honour them: What is the brotherhood, &amp; we will loue them: what it is to feare God, and we will feare him: and ſo forth. But Ieſus ſaid vnto him: <hi>Phillip, I haue beene ſo long time with you, and haſt thou not knowne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26420:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>me? he that hath ſeene me hath ſeene my Father.</hi> I cannot chalenge you, as Chriſt doth <hi>Philip, I haue beene ſo long time with you:</hi> for I haue bin ſeldome with you. Neither yet can your own Paſtours ſo chalenge you, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their bodily preſence, which you haue had much longer time, then Chriſt was with his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: becauſe they haue not ſo preached and ſhewed Chriſt vnto you, as Chriſt his father to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>And whence this deadly plague ſhould come, I knowe not, except partly from the the meaſels of the <hi>Gergeſites,</hi> contented, rather then they would bee at any coſt with Chriſt, to be without him: and partly from the ſeueritie of God againſt this ſinne and others: who deſpiſeth vs in this prophaneneſſe, as once his owne people, <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> in the eleuenth of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> the Lorde by the Prophet denouncing thus:<note place="margin">Zach. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>Then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26420:6"/>I ſaide, I will not feede you: that that dyeth, let it die: and that that periſheth, let it periſh.</hi> As Chriſt alſo telleth them in the 23. of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23, 38</note> that they are giuen ouer: <hi>Beholde</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your houſe it left vnto you deſolate. O my people</hi> (ſayth the Lord by <hi>Eſay</hi>) <hi>They which leade thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3, 12</note> 
               <hi>miſleade thee, and hide form thee the way of thy pathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet lo (deerely beloued) ſome parte of your pathes, as a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that paſſeth by, and is content to go a little with you, to ſhewe you the way that GOD hath ſhewed him. <hi>For God that commaundeth the light to ſhine out of the darkeneſſe</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4, 6</note> the ſecond to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> chap. 4. ver. 6.) <hi>is he, which hath ſhined in our hearts, to giue foorth the light of the knowledge of the glorie of God in the face of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And hee it is which hath lighted our candle, not that we ſhould put it vnder a bed or vnder a buſhel, but on a candleſtick,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26420:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>that it may giue light vnto the whole houſe. And, lo, now it ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vpon your candleſtick, to ſhew you ſome parte of the way, which you muſt walke.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſteppe vvhereof, is this, <hi>Honour all men:</hi> the ſeconde this, <hi>Loue brotherly fellowſhippe, or the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood:</hi> the third this, <hi>Feare God:</hi> and the ſourth and laſt this, <hi>Houour the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it ſeemeth this laſt point needed not to haue bin added by the Apoſtle, hauing ſpoken ſo largely at the firſt, ſaying, <hi>Honour all men.</hi> For is the King no bodie? Yes verily. hee is more then any beſides: and therefore hath a ſpeciall honour by himſelfe. In which reſpect the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith againe more diſtinctly and particularly of him, <hi>Honour the King,</hi> but of this in place.</p>
            <p>Wee haue therefore heere in the firſt place or point of this exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Honour all men,</hi> a generall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26420:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>honour, which reſpecteth all men, as well thoſe from whom it is due; as thoſe vnto whom it is due: that is to ſay, an honour which all men owe to all men; and each man to each, and euerie man: the King himſelfe not excepted, in that dutie which hee oweth to his meaneſt ſubiect. And therefore is hee called both by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane writers, as alſo by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and namely <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the 34. <hi>The ſheapheard of the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 34.2.</note> 
               <hi>VVo to the ſheapheards of Iſrael.</hi> And again. <hi>Heare the word of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>O ye ſheapheards.</hi> Where hee ſpeaketh as well to the ciuill, as Ecleſiaſticall Magiſtrate, as it is in the Pſalme, <hi>Thou didſt leade thy people like ſheepe by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 77.20.</note> The office therefore of Kings and rulers, is to leade and feed the people, and to doo them good.</p>
            <p>And this is the thing which ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally is here commanded, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto vs by the name of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; euen our dutie of dooing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26420:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>good vnto al that eſpecially need our good. For firſt that this is due, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by another Apoſtle, ſaying, <hi>Looke not euerie man on his owne things: but euery man alſo on the things of other men, Philip.</hi> 2. and 4. And againe,<note place="margin">Phillip. 2.4.</note>, to the Galathians, the 6, and 10. <hi>VVhile we haue time let vs do good vnto al, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe that are of the houſhold of faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> And in the third of the Prouerbs,<note place="margin">Prou. 3.27.</note> 
               <hi>VVithhould not good fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the owners ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when it is in thy power to do it.</hi> Where note, that hee calleth the needie the owners of thy good, or benefit, as due vnto them: the enemie himſelfe not excepted conſidered, not indeed as an enemie (for that is not poſſible, vnleſſe wee ſhould conſpire againſt our ſelues) but as a man, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth hee within the compaſſe of this honor of the Apoſtle, <hi>Honour all men.</hi> For this honor, as all other du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, muſt not onely bee pure and without hypocriſie, but full &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all her parts; not partiall, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26420:8"/>any, but including all, euen the enemie: as Chriſt alſo teacheth vs by his owne example, in the fift of <hi>Mathew.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5: 44, 45, &amp;, 48.</note> 
               <hi>But I ſay vnto you, loue your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie: bleſſe them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, &amp; pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hurt you, and perſecute you, that ye may be the children of your Father which is in heauen. For hee maketh his Sunne to riſe on the euill and on the good, and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt. Ye ſhal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee perfect as your father which is in heauen is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly that this duty done, <hi>is honour,</hi> it is plaine alſo by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Apoſtle, in the fifth of the firſt to <hi>Timothie. The elders</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which rule well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim: 5, 17</note> 
               <hi>are woorthie of double honor, ſpecially they that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi> Where hee ſpeaketh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly of the wage and maintenance of the miniſter, to be allowed vnto him according to the waight and worthineſſe of his worke and labor, as appeareth by that that followeth:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26420:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>For the Scripture ſaith (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>Thou ſhalt not moſell the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the corne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ 18.</note> And againe, <hi>The Labourer is worthie of his hire.</hi> And in the ſame place ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of poore widowes that liued well, and had no kindred able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them, hee commendeth them to the prouiſion of the Church, and ſaith,<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Honour widowes that are widowes indeede.</hi> And in the 15. of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> Chriſt very ſharpely reprooueth the Scribes and Phariſies, for looſing the bands of this dutie, and bringing this honour into contempt in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren towards their parents, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as were poore and needie, &amp; lay (as we ſay) vppon their childrens hands. For theſe hypocriticall &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous Maiſters had ſo preferred in holineſſe and worthineſſe, <hi>the gold of the Temple, before the Temple, and the gift of the Altar before the Altar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could ſweepe away the gold and the gifts, and turn them to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26420:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the maintenance of their pompe and pleaſure; that the people as (they taught them) did euer well to <hi>bring, bring.</hi> And howe euill ſo euer they were, and whatſoeuer euill they had done, as a thiefe that robbeth on the Plaine, yet if the Prieſt had receiued their gifts, and ſanctified them in the Temple, they were as ſafe (as they thought) and as well ſhrowded in this hipocriſie from all danger of the wrath of God, as the theefe is in his den, as the Lorde alſo by the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> obiecteth to them.<note place="margin">Iere. 7.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this went ſo farre (as I ſayde) that if a ſonne, or a daughter, (who themſelues had ſomewhat, and had their father and mother relying on them) had carried all to the Temple, and left themſelues ſo needie, that ſcarcelie, or not at all they were now able to relieue their Parents, yet all was well. For if the father or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complaining for maintenaunce, the ſonne had aunſwere, <hi>Gift,</hi> as it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26420:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>is in the fifteenth of <hi>Mathew,</hi> or as in the ſeuenth of <hi>Marke, Corban,</hi> that is <hi>gift:</hi> (The Verb is wanting which muſt bee ſupplyed, thus, <hi>gift it is,</hi> or, <hi>become gift,</hi> and giuen alreadie, wherewith thou mighteſt bee hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and relieued at my handes:) he was <hi>free,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>faultleſſe,</hi> by theyr doctrine. VVho to eſtabliſh theyr owne Tradition, of freeing men from ſinne, in ſuch a caſe as this, had abrogate (as Chriſt char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them) the commaundement of GOD, ſaying, <hi>Honour thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thy Mother.</hi> And againe, <hi>I will haue mercie and not ſacrifice.</hi> This mercie therefore, comfort, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, which ſhoulde bee beſtowed vppon the needie parents, is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which the Sonne or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oweth vnto them, in caſe, more then gifts or ſacrifices vnto the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and therefore is honor in deed: which God ſo eſteemeth of, and ſo alloweth to bee done, that rather
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26420:10"/>then it ſhould not be don, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to want ſome part of his owne outward honor, as here we ſee.</p>
            <p>And in deede theſe, I meane the needie of all ſorts, ſpecially thoſe that concerne vs moſt, are the liuelie Images, which our Papall men, and great Phariſaicall doctours ſhoulde haue taught the people to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and to bring their gifts and preſents vnto, and not to the Church walles and windowes, to ſtockes and ſtones, Roode-loftes, and the like, ſtumbling at the ſame ſtone that their fathers did. For there is in the perſon of man aboue al other things, a certaine excellencie and dignitie, as the Image of God, ſo to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of vs, that wee preſerue it by all meanes poſsible. And therefore in the Lawe of murther it is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that hee that ſheddeth mans blood,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> by man ſhall his blood bee ſhedde, becauſe hee deſtroyeth the Image of God. <hi>VVhat is man</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26420:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>that thou art mindfull of him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.6. Heb. 2, 6, 7</note> 
               <hi>Thou madeſt him little inferiour to the Angels, thou crownedſt him with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and honour, and hast ſet him aboue the workes of thy handes.</hi> Which is as true of him that hath nothing (if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the right and prerogatiue of his creation) as of him that hath all things, and wanteth nothing. In the Lawe it is commaunded, that if the neighbours Oxe, or Aſſe goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, we ſhall turne them into the way. Hath God care of Oxen? Doubtleſſe he hath. But much more of the neighbour himſelfe. For after the ſame ſort Chriſt reaſoneth in the 12. of <hi>Mathew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maa. 12, 12</note> 
               <hi>VVhat man</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ſhall there bee among you, which if he ſhall haue a ſheepe fallen into a pit on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, will not take it, and lift it vp? How much more then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> better then a ſheepe?</hi> This betterne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> therefore and excellencie of mans creation muſt be honored and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of vs with all helps neceſſarie to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26420:11"/>maintaine it. For this is the greateſt honor that we can do vnto it.</p>
            <p>As in deed what greater ſhewe of contempt (which is contrarie to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) can there be then this, to turne away the face, and ſo little to regarde a thing, as not to beſtowe the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on it. Euen as they do which denie theſe duties of loue and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion towardes their needie bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. <hi>Giue to him that asketh, and from him that woulde borrowe of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math: 5, 2</note> (ſayeth Chriſt) <hi>turne not thou away. Is not this the faſt that I haue choſen</hi> (ſaith the Lorde by <hi>Eſay</hi> in the fiftie eight Chapter) <hi>to looſe the cruell bandes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 58, 6, 7</note> 
               <hi>and let the oppreſſed go free; to deale thy bread to the hungrie, when thou ſeest the naked, to couer him, and not hide thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh?</hi> And therefore the Prieſt and the Leuite deſpiſed the man which fell into the handes of Theeues, and lay wounded and half dead betweene <hi>Hiericho</hi> and <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> For they came by and looked on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26420:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>him (ſayth the text) as ſtumbling at a Dogge. But then it followeth, <hi>They paſſed by on the other ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 90, 32</note> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of him. As indeed what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contempt of his perſon then this, to paſſe ſo by, and to ſee him periſh. Like as it was honourable done of the Samaritane to take him vp, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, and prouide for him. A worke more acceptable, and more neceſſarie to bee done (as the caſe may require) then diuine Seruice it ſelfe vppon ſome Sabboth day: as Chriſt in manie places ſheweth vs, and namely in the third of <hi>Marke,</hi> in the example of the man with the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand.<note place="margin">Marke 3, 1, 2 3, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Out of which place we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus for the poore man, agaynſt the contempt of the Prieſt &amp; Leuite, that becauſe they did not ſaue life when they might, they did euen kill him. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemies of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior Chriſt watched to ſee if vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sabboth day he wold heale this man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26420:12"/>with a withered hande, he being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to do it, firſt to conuict their malice, reaſoneth thus: <hi>Is it lawful</hi> (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he) <hi>to do a good deed on the Sabboth day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 4</note> 
               <hi>or to doo euill? to ſaue life or to kill?</hi> Where hee yeeldeth thus much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, that if hee had not done that good deed to the poor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent perſon, he had done euill; and if he had not giuen life to that dead member of his, he had ſo farre killed him. And therfore, as here he healeth him, ſo it is ſaide in the 8. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> that he healed all that were brought vnto him. And though hee were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſought, yet (opportunities obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) we neuer reade that he denied, or turned backe any.</p>
            <p>For where both theſe, as partes of dutie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37, 27 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al. 1, 17, 18</note> are commaunded vs, <hi>Depart from euill, and doo good: Ceaſſe from euill, learne to doe well:</hi> one alone is not ſufficient. And therfore in the 12 of <hi>Mathew,</hi> Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Hee that is not with mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 12, 30</note> 
               <hi>is againſt mee; and he that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26420:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>not with mee ſcattereth.</hi> And <hi>Salomon</hi> in the tenth of the <hi>Prouerbes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10, 26</note> 
               <hi>As Vineger</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>to the teeth, and ſmoke to the eyes, ſo is the ſlouthfull to him that ſendeth him:</hi> that is, hee of whom dutie is required to bee done, and doth it not. And though in the 9. of <hi>Marke,</hi> Chriſt there ſeemeth to ſay as it were the contrarie, <hi>Let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mhr 9, 40</note> 
               <hi>hee that is not againſt vs is on our part:</hi> yet hee meaneth thus, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth it by compariſon thus, hee is ſo farre foorth with vs, as hee is not agaynſt vs, and better then he who not onely is not with vs, but alſo agaynſt vs. For as dutie is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirelie kept in both theſe poynts, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from euill, and do good:</hi> ſo is it bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in both, as when wee not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie doo no good, but actuallie doo euill. And our Sauiour Chriſt in that place of <hi>Marke,</hi> ſpeaketh of one that was inclining and comming to the Goſpell, and did him and his Diſciples no harme, though as yet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26420:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>he did them no good, nor kept their companie, as there we reade.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Cain</hi> had not learned, as appeareth by his churliſh anſwer to GOD, <hi>Am I the keeper of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 4, 9</note> It might haue beene anſwered by God; Yes indeed art thou the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of thy brother, and to ſee to him, and therefore much leſſe ſhouldeſt thou haue killed him, as nowe thou haſt doubly done: firſt, by not kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him; and then in killing him.</p>
            <p>And doth not this brood of <hi>Cain</hi> line yet with vs? &amp; is not this voyce too often heard? <hi>Am I the keeper of my brother?</hi> muſt I looke to him? let him looke to himſelfe if hee will. And although his neede be neuer ſo great, and our hand neuer ſo ſtrong, yet for vs (as we ſay) hee may ſinke, or ſwim. Theſe care not who wring, <hi>Modo ſibi ſit bene,</hi> ſo they fare well. And their doing, is as their ſaying, (more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heathen wretches herein) <hi>Euery man for himſelfe, &amp; God for vs all:</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:26420:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>as if God were bounde to doo for them, and they will do nothing but for themſelues.</p>
            <p>And yet theſe bodies in which we liue, as it hath many members, ſo euerie member doth dutie one to the other. This houſe in which we now are, and ſerueth vs for this aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, is ſo built, that one ſtone &amp; iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſtayeth vp another. And theſe verie Bookes, in which wee reade, are ſo made &amp; compact, that letter ſerueth to leuer, to make ſyllables; and ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, words; and words; ſentences; &amp; by altogether wee reade, and learne knowledge. This dutie therefore of ſeruing one another, &amp; being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales men, not priuate-weals men, nature, and reaſon, &amp; heathen can teach vs. <hi>Non nobis ſolis nati</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>partim patria, partim parentes,</hi> and ſo forth. <hi>VVe are not borne onely for our ſelues, but partly our countrey, partly our parents, partly our friendes and neighbors will claime a right in vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:26420:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And indeede God and nature it ſelfe, hath eaſt all (almoſt) into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities and ſocieties, greater, or leſſer, as Cities and families, as wee ſee: the Lorde ſo ordering it at the firſt for neceſſitie ſake, as wee reade in <hi>Geneſis, Bonum eſt hominem non eſſe ſolum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>It is good for man not to be alone.</hi> Who therefore as hee receiueth his good from other, ſo ought hee to miniſter helpe, and doo good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And therefore if thou do ſay with <hi>Cain; Am I the keeper of my brother,</hi> it ſhall be anſwered, Yes indeede are thou the keeper of thy brother, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou muſt <hi>honour</hi> him, as the Apoſtle here commandeth, ſaying, <hi>Honour all men.</hi> And if thou do not ſo honour them as heere is taught, thou doeſt contemne them, and in contemning them doſt kill them: as Chriſt before teacheth thee in the third of <hi>Marke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where I may conclude, that it is not onely the fire of the wrath of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26420:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, which hath brought this deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation vpon this place, where yet we may beholde and ſee many heapes of ſtones and duſt, moyſtened no leſſe with the teares of the afflicted, then with the raine from heauen: but the careleſſe &amp; mercileſſe hearts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which ſtill ſuffer it ſo to bee. In whome if this of <hi>Peter</hi> had taken place, there ſhould now haue beene no ſigne of this deſtruction amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Specially, there beeing ſo many, who in the dayes of our peace haue receiued ſo much. For this of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Honour all men;</hi> being ſpoken generally to all, doth yet ſo require this honor to be done of all, vnto all, that he, that hath moſt, muſt do moſt; and he, that hath little, muſt doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his litle. <hi>VVhich if there be a willing mind firſt</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>it is accepted according to that a man hath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12</note> 
               <hi>and not according to that he hath not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus in doing this honour to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26420:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>all men, wee muſt obſerue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion which pertaineth to vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our portion. <hi>For of him, that hath receiued much, much ſhall bee required: and of him that hath receiued little, little ſhall be required.</hi> The ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer muſt beare more in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then the iuiſt or rafter, and if one talent may not bee digged into the ground, what ſhall be the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe euill ſeruants which haue hid many talents, but this, <hi>Take from them their talents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 25</note> 
               <hi>and binde them hand &amp; foote, and caſt theſe euill ſeruants into vtter darkneſſe, there ſhall bee wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping &amp; gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> And yet ſee in this parable, the euill ſeruant waſteth not his talent, nor abuſeth it vnto oppreſſion; but onely he vſeth it not at al, &amp; doth no good with it. For of that ſeed of <hi>Cain,</hi> which oppreſſe, kil, and deſtroy, <hi>which griende the face of the poore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa, 3, 15 Amos: 2.6</note> as it is in the third of <hi>Eſay:</hi> and in the ſecond of <hi>Amos, which ſell the iuſt for money, and the needie, pro pari
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26420:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Calceorum, for a paire of ſhooes;</hi> I will ſpeake no more.</p>
            <p>Onely thus, for the order of this honour, he, whoſe hand hath moſt, his charge is moſt: and he that hath little hath charge for a little. Which if euerie man would looke vnto, as here wee are commanded to <hi>Honour all men:</hi> Lord, what a heauen (as I may ſo ſay) of help would there bee amongeſt vs? and howe true would the prouer be be, <hi>Homo homini Deus: Man is God to man.</hi> And the poore of the Land ſhould be prouided for, (as we are commanded in the 15. of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi>) euen by the ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of manies aboundance.<note place="margin">Deut. 25.7. &amp; ſeq.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And yet againe, as in this <hi>honour</hi> heere required, wee obſerue a proportion in thoſe from whom it is due: ſo likewiſe ought wee to do in, and as concerning thoſe, vnto whome it is due: and all muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all, but not alike; euen as all are bounde vnto all, but not alike.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26420:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>And therefore the Apoſtle in the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of the firſt to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Tim. 5, 8.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them deereſt, who are neareſt to vs: <hi>If there be any</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that prouideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his owne houſhold, hee hath deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the faith, and is worſe then an infidell.</hi> And in the 6. verſe of the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>If any faithfull man or faithfull wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>haue widowes,</hi> meaning of their kinne, and which are neere vnto them, <hi>let them miniſter vnto them,</hi> that is, let them helpe and releeue them, <hi>and let not the church bee charged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the father, oweth more to the childe; the husband, to the wife; the brother, to his brother; yea, the friende to his friende; (becauſe hee hath bounde him by a ſpeciall band) then to any other. And if theſe will not honor theſe, protect and defend, helpe, comfort, and nouriſh theſe, (as too often we may ſee this honor wanting) it is becauſe we are fallen into the laſt times; of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26420:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>forewarned they ſhould bee greeuous, it would euen greeue any godly minde to ſee the maners of them:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.3</note> 
               <hi>For men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhalbe louers of themſelues, couetous, proude, boaſters,</hi> and ſo forth. At length he addeth, <hi>without naturall affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which in a ſort doubtleſſe may be extended euen to thoſe alſo, which deny this honour of which we ſpeak vnto their ioynt-neighbours, and fellow-citizens: vnto whome by a ſpeciall band they owe more, then to anie other; by reaſon of the mutuall ſocietie and c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oiuuction of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the bodie politique, wherein they are placed. And therfore ought they more eſpecially to reioyce and ſuffer one with another, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good one of another, becauſe the help or hinderance, the honour, or rebuke of any member redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the whole body, in which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member hath his part: as <hi>Paule</hi> alſo ſpeaketh of the naturall bodie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:26420:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And this made <hi>Moſes</hi> firſt ſo ſeuere and couragious againſt the <hi>Egyptian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 7, 23, &amp;c.</note> wh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o he ſlue in defence, &amp; auenging the cauſe of one of his brethren: and afterwardes ſo carefull to agree his Countri-men and brethren, which ſtroue togither, ſaying, <hi>Sirs, we are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, why do ye wrong one to another.</hi> A great wrong, &amp; much dutie broken, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a brother ſhal wrong a brother; a neighbor, his neighbor; one towns man an other; a citizen, his fellow ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen: when enuie, &amp; debate, deceit, and oppreſsion ſhall raigne amongſt them, as ſtrife in the members of the ſame body: which reacheth home. <hi>For if ye bite</hi> (ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle) <hi>and deuoure one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal 5.15</note> 
               <hi>take heed leaſt ye be conſumed one of another.</hi> Which is the plague of the people mentioned in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3. <hi>Oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met in populo alter alter<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>u; quiſque proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſuum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 3, 5</note> 
               <hi>One ſhall oppreſſe another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people; each man his neighbour.</hi> As alſo in the 9. of the ſame prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.<note place="margin">Eſay 9, 20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1</note> 
               <hi>Euery one ſhall eate the fleſh of his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26420:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>owne arme; Manaſſeh, Ephraim; and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim, Manaſſeh; and both theſe against Iuda.</hi> And what of this? A citie, yea, a kingdom <hi>deuided in it ſelf ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12, 25</note>
            </p>
            <p>For it is not the honor of our times that can hold it vp; ſo light &amp; fooliſh and ful of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>attery, that I am aſhamed to name it: and yet many make a pride and a vertue of it: as if vertue were made of words, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wood of trees: &amp; therfore thus forſooth, father, &amp; bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; vncle, &amp; coſen, &amp; captaine, &amp; maſter, when indeed there is no ſuch maner link or ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d between the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And when they light on any of theſe, or any other their louers, &amp; friends, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom they will beſtow any of this court-holy-water, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cap &amp; knee, &amp; ſmooth &amp; fine words, &amp; low curtify, and broad imbracing, as if we would reach them a peece of our heart. But if any of theſe need our help, that is, honor in deed, then S. <hi>Iames</hi> his chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Abite cumpace, caleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ite, &amp; ſatura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ini: Goin peace, bee yee warmed, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26420:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>filled: but we giue them not the things that are fit for the bodie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I am, 2, 6</note> 
               <hi>VVhat profite is in this?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>And yet wee are ſo vſed to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, yea, reprochfull honour, that wee cannot leaue it: but euen when wee haue in hande ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe towarde men, they ſhall yet haue ſome of this honour therwhile to hide it, like that was beſtowed on our Sauiour: <hi>Haile King of the Iewes, and ſmite him on the face.</hi> Or, as <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, Haile Maister,</hi> kiſſe him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him.</p>
            <p>And yet (my brethren) neither this, nor any thing which before hath beene taught vs, is brought to abridge all outwarde honour, or ſhew of outward reuerence. Which wee acknowledge alſo to bee due, <hi>Suo modo, in a certaine manner,</hi> euen from all men, to all men, and from each man to each and euerie man, as is the other honour in fact be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. Which as it is indeed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26420:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>harder, and asketh coſt, and therfore alſo is more high and excellent: ſo this likewiſe is of that praiſe, &amp; price, that it ought not to be neglected, but embraced of vs. For God hath ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed his owne Image in vs, that each man moued with a proper and ſerious ſenſe of his ſinnes, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth his owne baſeneſſe, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth reuerence vnto him, which ſcarcely will acknowledge it to bee due vnto him, becauſe hee feeleth his ſinnes, as the other doth. And here is a right good ſtraining of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, when (as <hi>Peter</hi> willeth vs in the fifth Chapter of this Epiſtle) <hi>we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues euerie man one to another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5</note> According alſo to that golden rule of the Apoſtle in the ſecond to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians: Let euerie man thinke better of another then of himſelfe.</hi> And in the 12.<note place="margin">Philip. 2, 3</note> to the <hi>Romans: In giuing honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12, 10</note> 
               <hi>go one before another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This would take vs downe from the vpper ende of the table, and make
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26420:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>vs of our ſelues ſeeke the,<note place="margin">Luke 14, 7 8, &amp;c.</note> lower roomes firſt: and then the maiſter of the houſe woulde ſet vs vp highen. For this modeſtie is amiable, and this humilitie, honourable. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no maruaile if the good man of the houſe be ſo delighted with it, that he vouch ſafeth it the higheſt roome at the ende of the Table. This is meant by our Apoſtle in the 5. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and 5 verſ. of this Epiſtle, ſaying: <hi>Decke your ſelues inwardly with low lines of mind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5, 5</note> Marke, there is a maruellous decking, beautie, &amp; ornament in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie. But he ſaith, It is <hi>inward, in the hid man of the heart:</hi> and yet ſo, that it ſheweth it ſelfe outwarde: or elſe it were nothing worth, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the 27. of the <hi>Prouerbes, Better is open rebuke, then ſecrete loue.</hi> Yea, it ſo ſheweth it ſelfe in the bodie,<note place="margin">prou 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 5</note> that it decketh, adorneth and beautifieth the bodie, ſo as all men ſhall honour vs, when the bragger ſhall go by with contempt and ſcorne.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:26420:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>For ſo it is added by the Apoſtle, as a reaſon to perſwade vs to embrace this dutie: <hi>For God</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the proude.</hi> VVhat is that? To wit, this: Proude perſons looke for more then is due vnto them; but they ſhall not haue it. They would be honoured of all, <hi>Tanqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> minores Dii, as little Gods:</hi> but they ſhall bee broken of their willes. For as they haue meaſured vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo ſhall it be meaſured to them againe. They haue ſhewed in the pride of their mindes contempt and diſdain to others: and they ſhal reape it ſeuen fold again into their boſoms. For thus I take Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde that place of the <hi>Prouerbes,</hi> the third Chapter, the ſoure and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth verſe.<note place="margin">prou 3, 34</note> 
               <hi>VVith the ſcorner he ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</hi> Then it followeth in the verie words that <hi>Peter</hi> alleageth, <hi>But hee giueth grace,</hi> that is to ſay, fauour, loue, honour, and acceptation, <hi>both with God and men, vnto the lowlie.</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:26420:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>As it is ſaide of our Sauiour Chriſt, that hee <hi>grewe in wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 2, 52</note> 
               <hi>and ſtature, and in fauour both with God, and men.</hi> And why? Becauſe, as well in this lowlineſſe and humilitie, (no doubt) as in all other vertues, it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that hee ſhoulde bee our moſt perfect patterne, and leaue vs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that wee ſhoulde followe his ſteppes; and acknowledge no leſſe by his perſonall humilitie, then by his doctrine taught vs in the fourteenth of <hi>Luke,</hi> that <hi>hee that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth him ſelfe ſhall bee brought lowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 14</note> 
               <hi>and hee that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fie vpon therefore this outwarde flaunt of apparell, this bragging behauiour, and coy countenaunces of manie in this age of moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt manners, which would ſeeme to ſnatch honour to themſelues, and euen force it from vs. But they muſt remember (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth,) <hi>Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in honorante, non in honorate. Honour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26420:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>is in him that honoureth, not in him that is honoured.</hi> And therefore thou maiſt (happily) be deſpiſed of others, euen when thou deſerueſt to bee honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: much more ſhalt thou be ſure to go without this honour, when by this ambitious humour of crauing honour, thou deſerueſt no honour, but contempt.</p>
            <p>But heere wee are to obſerue a diſtinction. For as before in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of fact, hee owed moſt that had receiued moſt, to doo good vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers according to his quantity: ſo in this outward honour, or honour of outwarde reuerence, it falleth our contrarie, that hee oweth moſt vnto others, that hath receiued leſſe then others. For ſo it is in the ciuil bodies, and bodies politike, at in the natural bodie: wherein one member hath receiued more, or leſſe honour, then another; and all leſſe, then the head: as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſheweth vs in the 12. of the firſt too the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> that in a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26420:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>certaine varietie, as well in this, as in ſundry other things, there might be a maruailous conſent and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>For God is not the author of confuſion, but of peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.33,</note> And as one ſtarre differeth from another ſtarre in glorie, for the beauty of the heauens, ſo one man differeth from another in glory, to the beauty of the earth. And therfore there is now in ſome the honour of age, which is not in others: in ſome, the honor of wiſedom &amp; vertue, not in others: in ſome the honor of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, not in others: beſide the honor of maieſtie in the king &amp; magiſtrate, of whom we ſpeake not yet.</p>
            <p>And all theſe muſt haue their honour, euerie man, as hee excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth moſt, and hath moſt of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in himſelfe, as a marke or print of a certaine maieſtie, which God hath placed in him. And it was a peece of the confuſion threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened to <hi>Iuda</hi> in the third of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and not the leaſt parte of the confuſion,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26420:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>which at this day raigneth amongſt vs: <hi>Superbient p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſenem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 3, 5</note> 
               <hi>&amp; vilis in honor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium. The boy ſhall beare himſelfe bragge againſt the auncient, and the baſe againſt the honourable.</hi> And it greeued <hi>Iob</hi> at the heart;<note place="margin">Iob 2, 2, 3</note> and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ppe the heape of all his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, what once he had this honour, and no we had it not. <hi>Oh that I were</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>as in times past when God preſerued mee, when his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ig <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhined vppon my head.</hi> And afterwardes in the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>enth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe: <hi>VVhen I went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Gate to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate of iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſed them to prepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y. ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Streetos. The young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and bidde themſelues; and the ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe and ſtood vp.</hi> But in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chapter hee ſayth, <hi>But newe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ident me minore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pores, My younger laugh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> mee:</hi> and thoſe ſo baſe borne and vile, that, as there hee ſayth, <hi>VVhoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>athers I woulde haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned to ſette with the Dogges of my flocke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:26420:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This was <hi>Iobs</hi> caſe, to want that honour and reuerence, which once he had, &amp; had wel deſerued. Which if it be any of ours; (as doubtleſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was there more contempt, and leſſe honor yeelded vnto Superiors) let vs charge this ſinne vpon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours: yet ſo, as that wee wholie diſcharge not our ſelues of blame. For beſides that this plague is partly vpon vs,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.4</note> in the third of <hi>Eſay, Dab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> principes co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, I will ſet children to rule ouer them;</hi> and ſo indeede wee haue in many places rulers, no more able to rule themſelues and others, then women and children: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are deſpiſed of men, women, and children: there is alſo another plague mentioned by the Prophet in the next words, thus, <hi>Quifacinero ſe do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that is, <hi>I will ſet chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be their Rulers, which ſhall miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ouſly raigne ouer them.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the ſame chapter.<note place="margin">Verſe 13</note> 
               <hi>The babie oppreſſeth my people, and VVomen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26420:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>rule ouer them.</hi> And yet as very babes as they are in gouernment, and weak as women, to rule themſelues, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they ought to doo, they are ſtrong enough to oppreſſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and this maketh them to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed of the people. <hi>Vt ameris amabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſto,</hi> (ſaith the poet) <hi>If thou wilt haue loue, thou muſt beare thy ſelfe louely.</hi> And if thou wilt haue other to honour thee in high place, do thou ſtoupe downe to them, and honour them in thoſe roomes and places wherein they are, euen the meaneſt. Do not oppreſſe them, but relieue them (for this is the beſt honour, as before is proued) and ſhewe all kindneſſe and courteſie, and affabilitie towardes them. And thou ſhalt ſee that kindnes will beget kindneſſe; as <hi>Moſes</hi> was honoured of all the people. And yet it is ſaid that <hi>he was the mildeſt man in al the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Which doubtleſſe could not haue been, if in his high place he had ouerlookt them, and not rather
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26420:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>in all faith fulneſſe, loue, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, had looked to them, &amp; liued with them as a common friende.</p>
            <p>And therfore the king himſelfe alſo in the 17. of <hi>Deut.</hi> was commanded not to multiplie horſes,<note place="margin">Deut. 17, 6, &amp; ſeq.</note> nor augment his pompe ouermuch, leaſt he ſhuld waxe proude, <hi>and haue his heart lifted vp aboue his brethren.</hi> Wherefore, giue, you that are euen the greateſt, giue vnto the meaneſt their honour, and they ſhall giue you yours, <hi>Good meaſure</hi> (as Chriſt ſaith) <hi>preſſed downe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 6, 38</note> 
               <hi>ſhaken together, and running ouer, ſhall men giue into your boſome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 7, 2</note> 
               <hi>for with what meaſure you meate, with the ſame ſhal men meaſure vnto you againe.</hi> For otherwiſe euery man doth beare a kingdome in his breaſt, how ſoeuer his outward obedience or reuerence may be wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted from him.</p>
            <p>And yet may, and muſt the Ruler, and euerie ſuperiour maintaine his place, and ſhew himſelfe, as he is, in keeping the grace, and grauitie; the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26420:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>port, and ſupport of a ſuperiour: as it is ſaide of a Roman gouernour, that he bare vp the Common-weale with his brow or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Which no man may impute to pride or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſtie for it is maieſtie. Therfore <hi>Salomon</hi> maketh a compariſon in the thirtieth of the <hi>Prouerbes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30, 29 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>There bee three things</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wel theyr going, yea foure which haue a comely gate, an olde Lyon migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie among Beaſtes, and turneth not at the ſight of any: an Horſe that hath his Bellie taken downe: a Goate, and a King againſt whome there is no ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vppe.</hi> And therefore it is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled in another place, <hi>Ne ſis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis in ſapientia tua.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19.</note> 
               <hi>Bee not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowly in thy wiſedome, nor out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite with thy ſelfe for thy place:</hi> leaſt it bee true which is ſaide, <hi>Tanti eris aliis, quanti tibi fueris: Thou ſhalt bee iuſt ſo much eſteemed of others, as thou</hi> (in this ſenſe) <hi>eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thy ſelfe.</hi> And therefore it was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26420:24"/>commanded <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12</note> being a yong man, to ſhew himſelfe graue in his miniſtrie. <hi>Let no man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe thy youth.</hi> That is, ſee thou giue none occaſion by any ouer familiar, light, or looſe behauiour, that any ſhould deſpiſe thy youth. And no leſſe the Paſtour of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, then the Paſtor of the church, in the perſon of <hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.15.</note> is commanded thus: <hi>Theſe things ſpeake and exhort, and rebuke with all authoritie. See that no man deſpiſe thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the ſuperiour muſt know what honour hee hath; and much more what honour he oweth to the inferiour, and pay it: and the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our for his parte muſt doo the like. And all men (as <hi>Peter</hi> heere ſayth) muſt <hi>honour all men.</hi> A neceſſarie doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, for al, who in that ſtate of fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſement, which wee haue in the heauenly city of our God and King, haue, or ought to haue our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation (as <hi>Paul</hi> had his) <hi>in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 3, 20</note> or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26420:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>heauenlie, or as in heauen alreadie, according alſo as we pray,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thy will be done, in earth as it is in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much of the firſt ſtep of theſe foure duties heere required. Which is as farre as at this time I can go with you. Now let vs pray.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <head>THE SECOND Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. Pet. 2.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Loue brotherly fellowſhip.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole verſe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it ſelf into foure principal parts, which are ſo many ſeuerall exhortations, of the firſt, in theſe wordes, <hi>Honour all men,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:26420:25"/>wee haue ſpoken alreadie, and are now come vnto the ſecond, in theſe words, <hi>Loue brotherly felowſhip,</hi> or, as I had rather interpret them, according to the plain ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Greek worde, thus, <hi>Loue the brother hood:</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the word which the Apoſtle vſeth not vnto the minde &amp; affection of him that loueth, or the vertue of louing, as it ſeemeth our Engliſh tranſlation here doth: but to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren themſelues, which muſt bee loued.</p>
            <p>For as before he had ſhewed vs the matter, or, as we call it, the ſubiect of our honour, ſaying, <hi>Honour all men:</hi> and afterwards will ſhew vs the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our feare, ſaying, <hi>Feare God:</hi> and laſtly, the ſubiect of a particular and more eſpeciall honour, ſaying, <hi>Honour the King:</hi> ſo here he ſheweth vs the ſubiect or matter of our loue, or, if ye will, the perſons on whom our loue muſt work, to wit, the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: euen the whole ſociety of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26420:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>So as, (a litle to inuert our own tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and yet to keep as neere as we may) in ſteed of this, <hi>Loue brotherly fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip,</hi> we may read thus, <hi>Loue the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of brethren.</hi> So we name the whole ſtate of the Commons of the realme, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munaltie: and ſo here, the whole ſtate of the brethren, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one felowſhip, <hi>the brotherhood,</hi> or, <hi>felowſhip of brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in this ſentence we haue to obſerue generally, theſe two partes, The brethren, which muſt receiue our loue: and, The loue it ſelfe, which we owe vnto them.</p>
            <p>And touching the brethren, firſt, we ſee them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended to vs by the name of <hi>brotherhood,</hi> which is a ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or felowſhip of brethren, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuch (according to the force of the worde which <hi>Peter</hi> vſeth) I ſay, ſuch brethren as lay in the ſame belly with vs. Euen as in deed we haue all but one mother, <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (as ſayth the apoſtle in the 4. to the <hi>Gal.</hi>) <hi>which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26420:26"/>is aboue,</hi> and yet beneath, the <hi>Church</hi> ſcattered throughout the worlde,<note place="margin">Gal. 4, 26</note> 
               <hi>which is</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the mother of vs all.</hi> In her wombe we are begotten, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne anew</hi> (as <hi>Peter</hi> before ſaieth) <hi>not of mortall ſeede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1, 23</note> 
               <hi>but of immortall, by the worde of God. VVho of his owne will</hi> (as <hi>Iames</hi> alſo ſayeth) <hi>begatte vs by the worde of truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1, 18</note> 
               <hi>that wee ſhould be the first fruites of his creatures.</hi> And to our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the promiſe made in the foure and fiftieth of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 54, 13</note> 
               <hi>And all thy children ſhall be taught of the Lorde, and much peace ſhall bee to thy children.</hi> Thus all that are taught of God, and haue obeyed his worde, are brethren both by father and mother; and the whole number ioyned in one ſocietie or fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, is the brotherhood: which alſo is called the <hi>houſholde or familie of fayth. VVhile we haue time</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle in the ſixt to the <hi>Galathians</hi>) <hi>let vs do good vnto all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10</note> 
               <hi>ſpecially vnto thoſe that are of the familie of faith.</hi> And againe in the thirde to the <hi>Epheſians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ 3, 14</note>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:26420:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>For this cauſe I bow my knees vnto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lorde Ieſus Christ, of whom is named the whole familie in heauen, and in earth.</hi> And the bande of this <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie,</hi> or coniunction of brethren, is faith and holineſſe, in that heauenlie vocation, vnto which they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. In which reſpect they are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (as before we heard) <hi>the familie of faith, and faithfull brethren in Christ; and holie brethren.</hi> In the firſt to the <hi>Coloſsians, Paule an Apostle of Ieſus Christ, by the will of God and Timotheus our brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1, 1, 2</note> 
               <hi>To them which are at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe, Saintes and faithfull brethren in Christ.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.1</note> And in the third to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, Therfore holy brethren, partakers of the heauenlie vocation, conſider the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle and high Priest of our profeſsion, Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVherfore let not thine eies wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſeeke thy loue; but ſee who are ioyned in fayth &amp; holineſſe, and they are the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and there thou muſt faſten thy whole deſire. It is not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26420:27"/>in all the worlde beſides, that thou muſt ſo delight in, as in them. For tell mee, if anie thing bee ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, or commended to vs, as the brethren, or ſome dutie which pertaineth to them?</p>
            <p>Heere onelie wee except the loue of the Father: which yet is reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and, as it were, accompliſhed in the loue of the brethren. If <hi>yee loue mee</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>keepe my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 14, 15</note> And, <hi>This is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 15, 12</note> 
               <hi>that yee loue one another, as I haue loued you.</hi> And againe, <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13, 35</note> 
               <hi>if yee haue loue one to another.</hi> As if the loue of the brethren were the loue of Chriſt: becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in them, yea, dwelleth in them, and they in him; hee is one with them, and they with him; by a true, and reall coniunction (though the ſame not naturall, and carnall, but ſpirituall) as in the ſeuenteenth of <hi>Iohn, I pray not for theſe alone, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26420:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>for them alſo which ſhall beleeue in mee through their woorde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 17, 26 21, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>That they all may bee one, as thou, O Father in mee, and I in thee: euen that they may bee alſo one in vs; that the worlde maie beleeue that thou hast ſent mee. And the glorie that thou gauest mee I haue giuen them, that they maie bee one, as wee are one, I in them, and thou in mee, that they may bee made perfect in one, and that the worlde may knowe that thou hast ſent mee, and hast loued them, as thou hast loued mee.</hi> And ſo the Church conſidered with her head, is myſticall Chriſt, or Chriſt in a myſterie; and ſo called by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the twelfth of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.12</note> 
               <hi>For as the bodie</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is one, &amp; hath many members, and all the members of the body, which is one, though they bee many, yet are but one body: ſo is Chriſt,</hi> that is to ſay, Chriſtians, in one ſociety, euen the Church, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a bodie, but with her head Chriſt. Who, by an excellency of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26420:28"/>head aboue the members, giueth name vnto the whole, and it is called Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Hence commeth this acceptation in the ſecond of <hi>Zacharie, Hee which toucheth you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 2, 8</note> 
               <hi>toucheth the apple of his eye.</hi> And in the tenth of <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10, 42</note> 
               <hi>VVho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall giue vnto one of theſe little ones a cup of colde water onely in the name of a Diſciple, verelie I ſay vnto you, hee ſhall not looſe his rewarde.</hi> And in the ſiue and twentieth of <hi>Mathew:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25, 37, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>VVhen ſawe wee thee an hungred, and fedde thee? And when ſawe we thee a ſtraunger, and tooke thee in?</hi> and ſo forth. <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>inaſmuch as ye haue done it vnto one of the least of theſe my Brethren, yee haue done it vnto mee.</hi> And againe, <hi>VVhen ſawe wee thee an hungred, or a thyrst, or a straunger, or naked, or ſicke, or in priſon, and did not minister vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee?</hi> Theſe alſo are aunſwered, <hi>Verelie I ſay vnto you, in as much as ye did it not to one of the least of theſe,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26420:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>yee did it not to me.</hi> And in the ninth of the <hi>Acts, Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? it is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricke. And I anſwered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>who art thou Lord? and he ſaid, I am Ieſus whome thou perſecuteſt.</hi> Yet were they indeed the Chriſtians, and the bodies of the Saints, which he caſt into priſon, and lead them bound vnto <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But note I pray you out of the place of <hi>Mathew,</hi> that hee reckoneth there with the wicked, on his left hand, not for any other ſins, or for the want of that loue, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly appertaineth vnto himſelf, but that, which properly appertaineth vnto his brethren: becauſe it is beſt ſeene by louing his, howe wee loue him. For that ſometimes toucheth the purſe, where loue is beſt try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and that loue of the lip, Lord, Lorde, deceiueth many: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother haue neede, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26420:29"/>how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</hi> And therefore Chriſt our Sauiour doth not there challenge them ſimply and generally for the want of loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his brethren, but the outward workes and deedes of loue are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, <hi>of feeding and drinking, of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and harbouring,</hi> and the like. For loue being once inwardly inflamed, like fire, it breaketh out, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth outwardly, as neede requireth, or, it is no loue, and nothing worth; and ſometimes angereth more then rebuke.<note place="margin">Prou. 27, 9</note> Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith in the ſeauen &amp; twentieth of <hi>Prouerbs, Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is open rebuke then ſecret loue.</hi> And it gawleth the needie. Brother more to heare that in <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2, 16</note> 
               <hi>Departe ye in peace, be ye warmed, and be ye filled; when wee giue them not thoſe things which are fitte for the body,</hi> it greeueth them, I dare ſay, more that wee ſeeme thus to wiſh them well, and doo them no good indeede, then if wee were ſilent and ſayd nothing.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26420:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> reiecteth it thus, ſaying, <hi>VVhat profit is in this my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</hi> euen as wee may alſo, and ſay, What loue is this my brethren? it is no loue, but a ſhadowe of loue. For loue, though an affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is all in action, and ſuch kinde of action, that faith it ſelfe cannot ſhewe it ſelfe, nor worke without loue, which therefore is neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engendred of her, as the heat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and light which iſſue from the Sun, by which hee ſheweth his force and vertue. Therfore the Apoſtle in the fifth to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> writeth thus,<note place="margin">Gal. 5, 6</note> 
               <hi>In Ieſus Chriſt neither Circumciſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth any thing, nor vncircumciſion, but faith which worketh by loue:</hi> both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and outwardly, when and as oft as need requireth, and means are notwanting vnto the worke. And further, to note the propertie and worke of loue, in the firſt of the firſt to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> (hee ſayth) <hi>VVee giue thankes vnto God alwayes</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1, 3</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:26420:30"/>
               <hi>for you all, making mention of you in our prayers, without ceaſing, remembering your effectuall faith, and diligent loue.</hi> As if without labour and diligence, there were no loue: euen as faith, without effect or efficacie, and not effectuall, is no faith at all. And therfore in the matter of almes, <hi>Paul</hi> trieth the naturalneſſe (as hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) of the loue of the <hi>Corinthians. This ſay I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not by commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8, 8</note> 
               <hi>but becauſe of the diligence of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: therefore prooue I the naturalneſſe of your loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe thoſe works of loue do ſhew her moſt, which bring moſt good and profit to that which is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and none can adde to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie: <hi>Looke vnto the heaven</hi> (ſayth <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>and ſee and beholde the cloudes which are higher then thou.<note place="margin">Iob. 5.5. &amp;.7</note> If thou be righteous, what giueſt thou vnto him? or what receiueth he at thy hands?</hi> This alſo is another cauſe, why the Apoſtle without any expreſſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26420:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God, and the loue which we owe vnto him, turneth ouer our loue vnto the brethren, and ſetteth it a working there, as if wee had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doo with God: who onely of his own good pleaſure may haue pleaſure in vs, and in that wee doo; but no profit at al by vs, or by ought of ours: that onely appertaineth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Brethren. God may profit vs, and wee by loue may profit them, and God is pleaſed in this loue, as himſelfe loued in it; and therfore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed do we loue the Brethren. This <hi>Dauid</hi> expreſſeth in the ſixteenth Pſalme: <hi>Saue me, O mightie God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pſal. 16, 1, 2 &amp; 3.</note> ſayth he: (lo he fetcheth good from God, he bringeth none to him:) <hi>for in thee haue I put my truſt. O my ſoule, ſay vnto God, thou art my lord: good from me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth none to thee. All my delight is in the Saints that are in the earth, and in them that excell in vertue.</hi> This alſo I thought good to adde, leaſt any man ſhould thinke the Apoſtle in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26420:31"/>this loue, as onely due vnto the Brethren, had forgotten himſelf, or the firſt and cheefeſt parte of the Law, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue God aboue al things.</hi> For al loue, I confeſſe, is not due vnto the Brethren, but moſt ſpecially is declared in, and on the Brethren. For which cauſe the Apoſtle doubteth not to ſay expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as heere he doth, <hi>Loue the Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or fellowſhip of brethren.</hi> Who alſo, when hee biddeth to loue the the brethren, forbiddeth not to loue God; but rather, in bidding of the one, ſecretly, and by impliment, hee biddeth both, becauſe of neceſſitie they go together.</p>
            <p>Why then, deerely beloued, and why againe, are wee ſo vaine, to skippe the brethren, and to leaue that wee ſhoulde loue, and loue that wee ſhoulde leaue, or it will leaue vs, I meane the world and the things of the world. Of which <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">1. Ioan. 2, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Loue not the worlde, nor the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26420:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>things of the world. If any man loue the world, the loue of the Father is not in him:</hi> and much leſſe the loue of the Brethren, which are his children, and are not loued, but for the fathers ſake.</p>
            <p>Alas then for the Brethren, which haue loſt their loue of all the worldlings, who can loue nothing but this world, and the things which are in this worlde. But of this it is ſayde, <hi>All that is in the world (as the luſt of the fleſh, the lust of the eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 16, 17</note> 
               <hi>and the pride of life) is not of the Father, but of this worlde: and the worlde paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, and the luſt thereof.</hi> And therfore thriſe alas, yea, and a wo to them, becauſe they loue, and looſe their luſt: for the world periſheth to them, and they vnto the world. And therefore how much better were it for them if they could loue the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? of which is ſayde in the words next following,<note place="margin">Verſe 17</note> 
               <hi>But hee that fulfilleth the will of God abideth euer.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26420:32"/>And this is his will and commandement</hi> (as before we haue heard) <hi>that wee loue one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. 15, 12</note> 
               <hi>as hee hath loued vs:</hi> and ſo, louing togither, may liue togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, againe,<note place="margin">1. Ioan 3: 14</note> 
               <hi>VVe know that we are tranſlated from death vnto life, becauſe we loue the brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore for the loue of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we go not to the world, but to the brethren themſelues: for they will loue vs, vnleſſe they be turned from themſelues, and <hi>fall away from their owne ſtedfaſtneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.17.</note> Of which the Apoſtle admoniſheth, ſaying, <hi>Qui ſtat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor: 10, 12</note> 
               <hi>videat ne cadat: He that ſtandeth, let him take heed that he fall not.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looke well to your loue, my brethren, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to the faith of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> in the firſt Epiſtle and third chapter,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.5</note> 
               <hi>Euen for this cauſe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>when I could no longer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare, I ſent him</hi> (to wit <hi>Timotheus</hi>) <hi>that I might knowe of your faith, leaſt the Tempter had tempted you in any ſort, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26420:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>that our labour had been in vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> What if he had ſaide, <hi>That I might know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oft your loue?</hi> For faith, and loue, do go to gither; they dwel togither, &amp; they depart togither; they liue togither, &amp; they die togither. And therfore is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tempter as buſie about the one, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the other, and as mightie ouer the one, as ouer the other. And (look we wel vnto it) he ſhould not be ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Tempter, if dayly he tempted nor, &amp; at no time effected any thing: euen as too much is dayly ſeene, that thoſe that are baptized in the faith of brethren, make a mocke of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>Iſmael</hi> was circumciſed in the houſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and mocked <hi>Iſaac,</hi> there circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed togither with him. And <hi>Sarah</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>ſaw the ſonne Agar the Egyptians (which ſhe had borne vnto Abraham) mocking.</hi>
               <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 21, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> If <hi>Sarah,</hi> if <hi>Abraham,</hi> if <hi>Iſaac</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the ſeede of <hi>Iſaac</hi> this day lift vp their eyes, lo, the ſonnes of <hi>Agar, mocking:</hi> and ſo bitterlie,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26420:33"/>that <hi>Sarah</hi> our mother cannot abide it.<note place="margin">Verſ: 10</note> Wherfore ſhe yet ſaith, <hi>Caſt out the bond woman and her ſonne.</hi> And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the 4. to the <hi>Galat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it perſecution. <hi>But as then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he that was borne after the fleſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him that was borne after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,<note place="margin">Gal. 4, 29.</note> euen ſo is it now.</hi> Lo therefore, dearly beloued; ſome part of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, to heare and ſee the ſcorne of theſe baptized and onely baptized brethren, which point with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and mock home (as they think) ſaying, lo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy brotherhood who, as they taunt vs with their tongue, would teare vs with theyr teeth, in the time were come, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon &amp; ioint profeſsion.</p>
            <p>And yet if this were all it were the leſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 9, 6 2. The 3, 2</note> For <hi>all are not Iſrael which are of Iſrael. And all haue not faith,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. And hee meaneth it of thoſe that profeſſe the fayth. So all haue not loue, which profeſſe loue, and are vowed brethren. Yea, it is a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26420:33"/>note of theſe laſt times in the third of the ſecond to <hi>Timothie: This knowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1 &amp;c.</note> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that in the laſt dayes grieuous times ſhall bee at hand. For men,</hi> ſayth he, what men?<note place="margin">Verſe 5</note> members of the viſible church, &amp; profeſſed in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> faith: (for of other it were no maruell) <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen ſuch men ſhall bee louers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, couetous, proude, boaſters, curſed ſpeakers,</hi> and ſo forth, in a great ranke. In which to fill vp the number, are placed alſo theſe, Loue leſſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>no louers of them that are good,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Paule:</hi> no they cannot loue a good man for their liues. And therefore of theſe counterfets, the brood of <hi>Iſmael</hi> (almoſt) we looke for no better.</p>
            <p>But the Tempter to ſhew himſelfe hath gone yet further, to alter the ſeed of <hi>Iſaac</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their true loue, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting our eie-ſight, when we look on the brethren; iudging ſome to be worthy of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; &amp; otherſome (no leſſe worthy in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues, but to vs
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26420:34"/>as vnworthie) wee reiect and go by them, and hang the brows at them, as ſtraungers and enemies. And all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome oddes in ſome pointes, which are betweene vs,<note place="margin">Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5, 36, 37, &amp;c.</note> leſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times then that in the <hi>Acts,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> counſelled to take <hi>Iohn Marke,</hi> in viſitation; <hi>But Paule thought it not meete, becauſe hee had departed from them from Pamphilia, and went not with them to the worke.</hi> And there was ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch a heat betweene them both about this matter, that they parted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, ſo that <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas tooke Marke, and ſailed into Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus and Paule tooke Silas and departed.</hi> Two apoſtles ſo incenſed one againſt the other, that (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word <hi>Paroxiſmos</hi> may alſo ſignifie) they were, as it were in the ſit of an ague. And yet the matter not great. For <hi>Marke</hi> was a good man, and <hi>Paule</hi> might haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him; and <hi>Barnabas</hi> might haue left him, if they had beene pleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17</note> 
               <hi>The kingdome of God</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Paule</hi>)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26420:34"/>
               <hi>is not meate, nor drinke,</hi> (and yet the queſtion of our libertie in meat and drinke, which there hee handleth, was not ſmall) <hi>but righteouſneſſe, and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And <hi>in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>neither circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>auaileth any thing, neither vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but fayth which worketh by loue.</hi> Yet who may cure our <hi>Paroxiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> yea, our Schiſmes, and ioyne vs in loue vnto the Brethren, which haue, and holde Chriſt, and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt: &amp; yet for ſome other things, wherin we iudge them they are not for our companie; and ſtill wee will diſtinguiſh betweene brethren and brethren: and ſome we will take, and ſome wee will leaue to liue to themſelues: ſome wee will loue, and ſome we will hate. And ſo <hi>out of one mouth</hi> (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaieth) <hi>yea out of one heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3, 10, 11, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>proceedeth bleſsing and curſing. My brethrentheſe things ought not ſo to bee, Dooth a fountaine
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26420:35"/>ſend foorth at one hole ſweete wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and bitter alſo? Can the figge tree, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, bring foorth Oliues; or elſe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Figges? So can n o fountaine giue both ſalt water and bitter alſo.</hi> And ſo touching the brethren, we loue all, or none: and our loue to like thinges muſt bee alike; or elſe wee loue not as we ought.</p>
            <p>And ſo, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> heere ſpeaketh not ſingularly, or diuiſiuelie, but as it were, collectiuelie, ſaying, <hi>Loue the brethren,</hi> that is, all the brethren, euen the whoſe number of them, ioyned in one ſocietie, not one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. And <hi>Paule</hi> in the firſt to the <hi>Colloſsians: VVee giue thanks</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>to God, euen the Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1, 3.</note> 
               <hi>alwayes praying for you ſince wee heard of your fayth in Christ Ieſus, and of your loue towards al Saints.</hi> And Chriſt, to ſhewe how hee hath loued vs, all, and euerie one, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the ſingulars, and each ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in the generall, giuing vs alſo
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26420:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>the name of brethren, ſayth, as before wee heard out of the liue and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>Mathew.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 25, 40</note> 
               <hi>Inaſmuch as ye haue done it vnto one of the least of theſe my brethren, ye haue done it vnto me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 45</note> And againe, <hi>Inaſmuch as yee did it not to one of the least of theſe, yee did it not to mee.</hi> And in the ſeuenteenth of <hi>Iohn:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 17, 2</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe that thou gauest mee, haue I kept, and none of them is lost, ſaue the childe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that the Scripture might bee fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Where he deſcendeth to account for euerie particular, which the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had giuen him: and ſo muſt we, for euery brother, whome hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth vnto our loue.</p>
            <p>But note, I pray you, out of the place of <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 40</note> a diſtinction of brethren. For he ſaith, <hi>Vnto one of the least of theſe my brethren.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome are greater, and ſome are leſſe, not in the brother hood it ſelfe, or nature of brethren, wherein all are alike: but in ſome outwarde reſpects, wherein they may be, and are vnlike.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26420:36"/>as here in this place of <hi>Mathew,</hi> the 25. there is mention of <hi>hungrie,</hi> and <hi>thirſtie,</hi> of <hi>naked,</hi> and <hi>harbourleſſe,</hi> and priſoned brethren, who in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect are leſſe, as the Lord hath hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them, then thoſe brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are full, and clothed, houſed, and at libertie, hauing other furniture alſo ſomtime of pompe and dignitie. The one ſort Saint <hi>Iames</hi> in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his firſt Epiſtle calleth <hi>Brethren of low degree:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1, 9</note> 
               <hi>and the other he calleth rich.</hi> Thus, there are poore, &amp; abiect bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, low, and little: and there are great, and rich, and flouriſhing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: and we muſt loue all. But yet out loue is chiefly approued (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhewed) by ſuch outwarde works, and duties, which we do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our leſſer brethren; for our greater brethren need them not: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the members of the naturall bodie:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12, 23</note> 
               <hi>And vpon thoſe members</hi> (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hee) <hi>of the bodie which wee thinke to bee the leſſe honourable, wee put on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26420:36"/>more honour: and our vncomely parts haue more comelineſſe: for our comely parts need it not.</hi> Thus, the hunger, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, the wants and diſtreſſes, the bands and priſonments of our lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Brethren ſhould be our care, and the matter eſpecially to fire our loue: much leſſe ſhould wee ſet light of them, becauſe they are little. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> compareth the prophane rich men of the world, with the rich Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and reproueth the loue of the faithfull to whom hee writeth, for preferring the one before the other. And what do wee elſe, if in reſpect of their riches, their pompe, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, wee preferre in our loue, and the duties of loue, our greater Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the leſſe? but let vs heare his words:<note place="margin">Iam. 2, 1, 2, &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>My brethren</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>haue not the faith of our glorious Lorde Ieſus Chriſt in reſpect of perſon. For if there come into your companie a man</hi> (I adde, a brother) <hi>with a gold ring, and in goodly apparrell, and there come in alſo a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26420:37"/>poore man,</hi> (to wit, a brother) <hi>in vite raiment, and yee haue a reſpect to him that weareth the gay clothing, and ſay vnto him, ſitt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou neere in a goodly place, and ſay vnto the poore, ſtand thou heere, or ſit heere vnder my foote-ſtoole: are yee not partiall in your ſelues, and are become iudges which haue euill thought? Hearken my beloued brethren, hath not God choſen the poore of this worlde that they ſhould bee rich in fayth, and heyres of his kingdome, which he promiſed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue him? but yee haue deſpiſed the poore.</hi> Heere he toucheth the boyle. For there is a kinde of eſtimation, which belongeth vnto men of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the Lord hath diuided degrees in the world, ſome brethren hauing more honour, &amp; ſome leſſe. But our loue vnto all muſt bee alike, as well poore, as rich. And wee muſt haue ſomewhat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more care of the poore, that we exclude them not, for Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his reaſon, becauſe the greater number of vs, I meane the brethren,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26420:37"/>are poore, and not rich, weake, &amp; not ſtrong; baſe, and not honorable; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, &amp; not wiſe. <hi>Hearken my beloued brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath not God choſen the poore of this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 3</note> 
               <hi>that they ſhould be rich in faith, and heyres of the kingdome, which he promiſed to them that loue him?</hi> not that he excludeth the rich, but more commonly &amp; generally in this choyſe reſpecteth the poore, as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſheweth in the firſt of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians. Brethren</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you ſee your calling,</hi> that is, who,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.26 &amp; ſeq.</note> and what manner of men amongſt you, are called, and come vnto Chriſt, <hi>not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not manie mightie, not many noble. But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the worlde, to confounde the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weake things of the world to confounde the mightie, and vile things of the world, and things which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed hath God choſen, and things which are not, to bring to naught things that are, that no fleſh ſhould glorie in his ſight.</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:26420:38"/>And therefore I feare, if my heart giue a better welcome to a rich bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then to a poore, that I loue not the brethren as I ought. Wherefore let not the carnall and outwarde beautie of Brethren beguile our mindes. <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 45, 14 Hebr. 13, 2.</note> Angels may bee ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as in the thirteenth to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> and the beautie of a brother may be hid vnder a very ſorie weede.</p>
            <p>The ſame may bee ſaide for the weake brethren, of whome ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what already hath bin ſpoken. And therfore briefly thus: be their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe neuer ſo great, euen as of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Chriſt, and their infirmities neuer ſo many; lacke they know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or conſcience ſometimes in ſomethings (<hi>For who can ſay,</hi> ſayth <hi>Salomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20, 9</note> 
               <hi>I haue cleanſed my heart, I am cleane from ſinne:</hi>) Wee muſt take them with all their faults, as wee are taken, and loue them as wee are loued, and were loued, euen when
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26420:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>we were enemies, as ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: &amp; the weaker our brethren are,<note place="margin">Rom., 510</note> the more muſt be our care, and our burthen the greater to beare them and make them better. <hi>Brethren</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle in the ſixt to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if a man be preuented in any fault ye which are ſpirituall restore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal, 6, 1</note> 
               <hi>conſidering thy ſelfe leaſt thou alſo be tempeed. Beare yee one anothers burthen, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much touching the firſt general point of this ſentence, what, or whom we muſt loue, to wit, <hi>the brotherhood or fellowſhip,</hi> of brethren none excepted. Nowe ſomewhat of the loue it ſelfe, and ſo an ende.</p>
            <p>And firſt, when as the Apoſtle here ſaith, &amp; exhorteth, ſaying, <hi>Loue the brotherhood,</hi> hee meaneth not that the faithfull to whome hee writeth, and in whom he acknowledgeth all the graces of God, were ſimply void of loue, or that they had not ſome
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26420:39"/>loue alreadie, when he wrote vnto them: but that they ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in loue, and increaſe in loue, and loue more perfectlie then before. For otherwiſe for the Brethren to loue together, is as kind and as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, as for the birdes to flie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for the heardes to feede, and to lie together; yea, for the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body to liue &amp; moue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: for loue is as it were, the life and ſoule of the Brethren. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is <hi>monſtriloco,</hi> a monſter, to ſee Brethren not to loue together. And when it fel out otherwiſe in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> it ſeemed ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and ſtrange to the Apoſtle, that he maketh as it were, an outcrie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, as if they had loſt their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and almoſt their wits, that ſome brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fel out, &amp; others could ſuffer it. <hi>I ſpeake it to your ſhame</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is it ſo that there is not a wiſe man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6, 5, 6, &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>no, not one that can iudge betweene his Brethren? but a Brother
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26420:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>goeth to Lawe with a brother, and that vnder the Infidels. Now therefore there is altogether infirmitie in you, in that you go to Law one with another. VVhy ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer yee not wrong. VVhy rather ſuſtaine yee not harme? Nay, you your ſelues doo wrong, and doo harme; and that to your Brethren.</hi> There is the wonder.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake more diſtinctly of this loue, we may ſhortly conſider in it theſe three points before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, firſt the continuance ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the increaſe: and thirdly, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or rather the ſynceritie and puritie of our loue. For the firſt, in the thirteenth to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and firſt, <hi>Let brotherly loue continue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.1</note> ſaith the Apoſtle: that is, ſee that it breake not off but run in one threed, and hold together vnto the end. For the reward is certain. For as the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorteth the <hi>Galathians,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Gal 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let vs not be wearie of well doing, for in time wee ſhall reape, if wee faint not.</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:26420:40"/>So becauſe nothing is better then loue, let vs not be wearie of louing, for in time wee ſhall reape if we faint not.</p>
            <p>And indeed why ſhould we leaue ſo good a thing? which wee cannot do, but we are in danger to fall into the contrarie. For anger it ſelfe, what is it, but a breach of loue, of which the Apoſtle faith, <hi>Be angry and ſinne not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4, 26</note> 
               <hi>Let not the Sunne go downe vppon your wrath, neither giue place vnto the diuell,</hi> who quickly taketh it, and tempteth vnto diſcord.</p>
            <p>And beſides it is a goodly thing to ſee the ſtreame of loue runne cleare without troubling; as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the proſperitie, and aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the righteous, in the fiue and twentieth of <hi>Prouerbs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 25, 29</note> 
               <hi>As a fountain trampled with the feete, or a ſpring mard, ſo is the iuſt which is remooued before the wicked.</hi> The proſperitie of the iuſt, is the cleare ſpring, and the aduerſitie of the ſame, is the ſpring troubled.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26420:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>and euen ſo the courſe of our loue continued is the cleare ſpring, and it is a goodly thing to ſee it cleare, as ſtil it woulde bee, were it not for trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. And therefore <hi>Paule</hi> in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine holy impaciencie, and zealous deſire of the continuance of the loue of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> exclaimeth thus, <hi>Vtinam &amp; abſcindantur qui vos contur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal, 5, 12</note> 
               <hi>I woulde they were euen cut off that trouble you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo wee ought to looke the more vnto our loue, that it breake not with any brother that loueth vs, becauſe the kinde heart is ſooneſt, and deepeſt wounded, and the cure thereof is verie hard. Of which <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayeth in the eighteenth of the <hi>Prouerbs:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18, 19</note> 
               <hi>A brother offended is harder to win then a ſtrong Citie, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are like the barre of a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet wee denie not, but as the Sunne ſometimes is darkned by the Clowdes, engendred of ſome groſſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26420:41"/>exhalations from the earth: ſo the light of our loue is miſted; and the heat thereof rebated by ſome ſiniſter and corrupt affections of our fleſhly nature. And as in phrenetical perſons we ſee that they haue their <hi>lucida in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terualla, bright and calme inter miſsions,</hi> which are not in the nature of the diſeaſe: So the louing brethren haue <hi>turbida interualla, their troubled fittes,</hi> which are not in the nature of their loue And therefore, as the Sunne at the laſt breaketh through the miſt, and cloude: and thoſe that are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the phrenzie, returne to their madneſſe as before: ſo the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to their loue, which no more can bee parted, or depart from their hearts, then the light from the Sunne; or life from the ſoule, which is impoſsible. And therefore, as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> notwithſtanding his ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie pretenſes, yea, his purpoſes, and permiſsions, and at the laſt his owne fact in letting the Iſraelites go
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26420:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>out of his land, returned to his owne nature, repenting, where bee ſhould not, and followeth after the ſame people to bring them backe, whome himſelf by commandement had ſent away: ſo on the other ſide brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, notwithſtanding for a ſeaſon they haue a bent another way, which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from their loue, as blinded with errour, tempted by Satan, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with the violence of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: yet time will trie them, and if they bee brethren, they will come to themſelues, and their loue agained notwithſtanding ſome vnkindneſſe for a ſeaſon: <hi>For greater is hee that is in vs</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>then hee that is in the worlde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Iohn 4, 4</note> And as <hi>Paule</hi> in the fifth of the firſt to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5, 24 25</note> ſpeaketh of two ſorts of Miniſters, the one hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall, deceiuing the Church at the firſt, and prouing bad at the laſt, of whom he ſayth, <hi>ſome mens ſinnes,</hi> or faults, <hi>are open before hande, and go before vnto iudgement, but ſome m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:26420:42"/>follow af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the others ſuch, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and are neg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, and bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> their giftes for a ſeaſon, yet comming, to themſelues againe, and as it were reui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, doo afterwardes ſhewe the fruits of their labour, and approue themſelues to the Church of God; and of theſe he ſayth in the words next following: <hi>Likewiſe alſo the good workes are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest before hande and they that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee hid:</hi> So may wee ſay, comparing the brethren vnto this better ſort of Miniſters, that though ſome of them ſometimes breake off from that courſe of loue, which they ought to continue, and ſleepe in the forgetfulneſſe of their dutie (as of both ſorts of virgins, both the wiſe, and the fooliſh, it is ſayde they ſlep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yet the brethren euen all cope, haue Oyle in their Lampes, and their loue awaketh with them, and embraceth the brethren, whome before it did not. And the good workes of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:26420:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, which at their firſt calling appeared, and were manifeſt to all men, (yet altered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a time, and carried into other behauiors, and bee ſeeming the courſe which firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan) <hi>cannot be hid,</hi> as ſayeth <hi>Paule,</hi> but ſhall be ſeene to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>o ſuch at the laſt, as they were at the firſt. For loue breaketh through all lettes, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> couereth the <hi>multitude of ſinnes, ſuffering all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13, 7</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ning all things, hoping all things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing all things</hi> at the handes of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And with a godlie ſorrowe worketh repentaunce and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our owne offences towards them, <hi>with great care, yea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Cor. 7, 11</note> 
               <hi>with clearing of our ſelues, yea, with indignation, yea, with f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are; yea; with great deſire, yea with zeale; yea; with puniſhment,</hi> for reconciliation, till the ſtrong Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie bee wonne; and one contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though as harde to breake as the barre of a pallace, be yet broken a ſunder, and our ſelues reunited
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26420:43"/>in the loue of brethren. So all at the laſt was forgiuen, and forgotten, betweene <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his brethren; and their loue braſt out in teares, and they wept, and reioyced, and kiſſed, and embraced, and theyr hearts were comforted in the loue of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.<note place="margin">Gen. 45</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration which we haue of our loue, is the encreaſe of the ſame. Of the which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the fourth of the firſt to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4, 9 14</note> writeth thus: <hi>But as touching brotherly lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (fayeth hee) <hi>yee neede not that I write vnto you: for ye are taught of God to loue one another Yea, and that thing verelie yee doo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the brethren, which are through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Macedonia: but, wee beſeech you brethren, that you increaſe more and more.</hi> VVee are not therefore to ſtande at a ſtay in loue, but ſtill to walke forwarde from loue to loue. For this is the way of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and of it <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayeth in the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26420:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>fourth of the <hi>Prouerbs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4.18</note> 
               <hi>The way of the righteous ſhyneth as the light, that ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth more and more vnto the perfect day.</hi> And the right loue of brethren is as fire, which ſtill increaſeth, and inflameth them with a certaine natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection and inclination to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another, of which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the twelfth to the Romans ſaith.<note place="margin">Rom. 12, 10</note> 
               <hi>Bee affectioned to loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with brotherly loue.</hi> And this affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or inclination cannot ſtay it ſelf, vntill it come to the higheſt degree of loue, and leadeth vs to that which <hi>Peter</hi> requireth in the firſt Chapter of this Epiſtle, namelie,<note place="margin">1 Pet 1, 22</note> 
               <hi>That wee loue one another out of a pure heart, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementlie,</hi> or as our Engliſh tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation giueth it, <hi>Feruentlie, with all the heart, and with all the ſoule, and with all the might:</hi> and ſo our loue become zeale, which hath eaten vs vp, &amp; we all in a zeale do loue the brethren. Which condemneth (my brethren)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26420:44"/>the loue of theſe times, the laſt I thinke; in which it is come to paſſe, as our Sauiour foretold, that <hi>becauſe iniquitie ſhall abounde, the loue of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> yea, manie brethren, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid towards brethren is waxen colde.</p>
            <p>But (to come to the third and laſt point) whether wee loue little, or whether wee loue much, according to the meaſure of grace which wee haue receiued, let vs yet loue pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and that loue which wee haue, let it bee loue in deede. <hi>Not euerie one</hi> (ſayeth Chriſt) <hi>that ſayth vnto me. Lorde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Lorde,</hi> that is, which profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe my ſeruaunt, <hi>ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Kingdome of Heauen: but hee that dooth the will of my Father which is in Heauen.</hi> Not euerie one that ſayeth <hi>Brother, Brother,</hi> ſhall haue the prayſe of true loue, but hee that will doo for his brother in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20, 9, 10.</note> Not as <hi>Ioab,</hi> which ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Amaſa,</hi> and ſayde, <hi>Art thou in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26420:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>health my brother?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Faigned loue</note> 
               <hi>and hee tooke. Amaſa by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eard with the right hand, to kiſſe him. But with his ſword he ſmote him in the fifth rib, and ſhedde out his bowelles to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>round.</hi> This was not loue, but diſſimulation, which ought to bee farre from the loue of brethren. So the Apoſtle commaundeth in the twelfth to the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <hi>Let loue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be without diſſimulation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12, 9</note> And <hi>Peter</hi> in the firſt Chapter of this Epiſtle, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth brotherly loue vnfaigned;<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1, 22</note> 
               <hi>VVith brotherly loue vnfaigned</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>not of a pure heart loue ye one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feruently.</hi> Therefore this loue which kiſſeth; &amp; killeth, which mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, and burieth all in a day, is not worthy of mention with the loue of brethren.</p>
            <p>No, nor a better loue then this:<note place="margin">Idle loue.</note> a better, I call it, becauſe it doth no harme: and yet is not good inough, becauſe it dooth no good. <hi>If a brother or aſiſter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iames</hi>) <hi>be naked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2, 15, 16</note> 
               <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of daily foode; and one of you ſay
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26420:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto him, Depart in peace, beeye war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and be yee filled: not withſtanding, yee giue them not thoſe things that are needefull for the body, what helpeth it?</hi> This lip-loue Saint <hi>Iames</hi> refuſeth: and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> wil none of it, ſaying, in his firſt Epiſtle and third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>My little children, let vs not loue in word, neither in tongue onely; but in deede and in truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioan. 3, 18</note> As if there were no trueth in loue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the deede, if do it can, and doth it not.</p>
            <p>And yet againe there is another loue not aright, which doth ſome good, and leadeth to ſome duties which are profitable, but not for loue ſake; but becauſe wee receiued ſome good before, or may receiue profit by the fame againe. And this we may call a ſeruile loue,<note place="margin">Seruile loue.</note> becauſe it worketh for wages and nothing els; and is no better (as our Sauiour tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs) but that ſinners and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans may haue the like.<note place="margin">Matth, 5, 46, 47. Luke 6, 32, 33.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:26420:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But to leaue theſe loues, which are none of ours, &amp; to note that which indeede the Apoſtle meaneth,<note place="margin">Simple loue</note> it is a ſimple loue, pure, &amp; voyde of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, &amp; loueth the brethren for the brethrens ſake. Of which we may ſay as <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſpeaketh in the fourteenth of <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> of the ſenſe and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the mind towards mirth, or mourning: <hi>The mind</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth his own bitternes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14, 10</note> or what is better to it ſelfe: <hi>and in the mirth therof no ſtrange thing doth mixt it ſelfe.</hi> That is, it trieth al things, and taketh what it loueth, &amp; leaueth what it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not. And euen ſo this loue of brethren, it hath her proper iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; nothing it aloweth but what is like hir ſelf. It admitteth no reſpects of rich or poore; wiſe, or vnwiſe; ſtrong, or weak; profitable or vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: but looketh to the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bood or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of brethren (as <hi>Peter</hi> requireth) &amp; in the name of brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Chriſt ſpeaketh in the tenth of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26420:46"/>
               <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10</note> that is, as brethren, and in the onely nature of Brethren, it em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth them, and nothing in them beſides. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaluteth <hi>Timothie</hi> thus, <hi>Vnto Timothie my naturall Sonne in the faith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1, 2</note> ſo calling him, becauſe he had a true and a naturall faith. For there is a naturall faith, which bringeth foorth a naturall loue, of which wee ſpeake: and there is a baſtard faith, of which is ingendred a baſtard loue of falſe Brethren. Theſe alſo are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, but they are not of vs: and how little worth their loue is, I neede not ſpeake: the white of in egge, or a ſticke hath as much taſt as it. And theſe, as they lie in out way, needes wee muſt deale with them but ſtill we ſcare them, as a quauer mice that ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth vnder vs, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other they will deceiue vs. The Apoſtle in the eleuenth of the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> reckoning vp all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illes, to make vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the heape,<note place="margin">1. Cor 11, 26</note> at laſt addeth this; <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perilles
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26420:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>amongſt falſe brethren.</hi> And who of vs my Brethren, in caſting vp the ſumme of all our troubles, can leaue out this, <hi>In perils of falſe brethren</hi> or, if for the preſent wee can, the time may come that it may be added. For the broode of <hi>Iſmael</hi> doth ſpawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace. <hi>Hee that eate bread with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41, 10 Ioan. 13, 18</note> 
               <hi>hath lift vp his heele againſt me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſaith Chriſt. And how ſhould anie Chriſtian looke for better? <hi>Moſt men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in the twelfth of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs</hi>) <hi>Do prayſe each man his own kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but who can finde a faithfull man?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3, 6</note> to wit, which ſheweth ſo much, as hee ſaith he is. Thus many ſay they loue, but proofe maketh all. <hi>VVhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor, 8, 24</note> in the ſecond Epiſtle and eight Chapter) <hi>Shew towardes them</hi> (to wit, <hi>Titus,</hi> and another brother ſent vnto them) <hi>ſhew</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>towardes them, and before the Churches, the proofe of your loue, and of the reioycing that wee haue of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:26420:47"/>
            <p>And what prooſe or teſtimonie of our loue (my Brethren) ſhall I call for heere? ſurely none at this time but this, which none will denie, but loue will yeelde it, or none at all; it is ſo light, it is ſo little: and yet I would to GOD our loue would yeeld it. And this it is, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that at the leaſt we would come together, and ſee one another, and talke together, as louing brethren, of our father, and of our mother, and of our elder Brother, in whome, and whoſe loue wee are adopted chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; of theyr loue towardes vs, and our faith towards them; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of our loue one towardes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; of our neceſſities, of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, of our ioyes and comforts, of our hope, of our happineſſe, &amp; of the crowne, of our inheritaunce laide vp in heauen; &amp; further, to inſtruct, to exhort, to comfort, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and edifie one another: With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which I ſee not how loue can
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:26420:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>worke. Wherefore the Apoſtle in the tenth to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth thus:<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 24, 25</note> 
               <hi>Conſider</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>one another, to prouoke vnto loue, and to good workes.</hi> Then hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the meane. <hi>Not forſaking</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the fellowſhippe that wee haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues, as the manner of ſonne is.</hi> And who are thoſe ſome, but euen wee, which ſhoulde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider one another to prouoke vnto loue, and to good workes; which wee do verie little; and all becauſe wee forſake the fellow ſhippe that wee haue, or ſhould haue amongſt our ſelues, each man contenting himſelfe with himſelfe, when law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and without let, wee might ioyne with many Brethren. Did Chriſt ſo, who neuer (almoſt) went without his Brethren? or, did <hi>Paul</hi> ſo, who ſo earneſtly prayed for a iourney to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee the faithful, <hi>For I long</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſee you, that I might beſtow among you ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26420:48"/>gift; that you might be ſtrongthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> that is, <hi>that I might be comforted,</hi> (ſaith out) Tranſlation) <hi>together with you.</hi> But the words of the Originall I interpret thus, <hi>That there might be ioynt exhortation amongſt you,</hi> that is that, I might exhort together with you, or, ioyne my exhortaion togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with yours. For this is the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gift, which beforech ſaith, <hi>he reth to beſtow vpon them, by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tall faith:</hi> that is, by each others gift and knowledge in the faith, or doctrine of faith, both theirs and his.</p>
            <p>But all are not Apoſtles, all are not miniſters. Yea, but are all brethren, as the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and the Apoſtle in the ſift of the firſt exhorteth thus:<note place="margin">1. Theſ 5, 11</note> 
               <hi>VVherefore exhort one another, and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one another euen as yee do.</hi> Which how can it be better done, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we come together? Which though it be not alwaies, nor cannot be, yet as ofte as it may bee, let it bee, my brethren; and when it may not be,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:26420:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>let it be, as it may. And howe is that? let the hand be the mouth, and the penne our ſpeech; and our Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ftles and Letters, as the liuely cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of our hearts and mindes, let them preſent vs vnto the brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren. For I am aſhamed (almoſt) to thinke that wee are not aſhamed of ſo many bunches and bags full of Letters, written onely for the things of this periſhing life, and ſcarſe one or two in a yeere (if anie at all) ſent, or receiued of this kinde, I meane, concerning the loue of Brethren. As if neither Saint <hi>Peter</hi> here, nor any Apoſtle beſides, had euer ſaide; <hi>Loue the brotherhood:</hi> or, as if we could loue them, and do nothing for them, neuer ſo much as fee them, ſpeake with them, or heare how they do.</p>
            <p>And this (deerely beloued) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth our greater and publike aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (which what are they alſo
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26420:49"/>but certaine holy communications betweene God, &amp; his people, when either hee, by the word preached, doth ſpeake vnto vs; or wee, by our prayers do ſpeake vnto him?) this I ſay maketh them ſo colde and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that afterwards wee putte our ſparkles on the cold hearth, &amp; ſingle our ſelues one from another, &amp; haue not theſe priuate and leſſer meetings betweene our ſelues, to confer of the things which we heard before. As if before we had aſſembled but for a faſhion onely: which is not to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, but to diſſemble. <hi>Paul, though abſent in the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſſi. 2, 5</note> 
               <hi>yet was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the ſpirit,</hi> reioycing (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſayth) and beholding the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> in comming together. But wee, as preſent in the body, but abſent in the ſpirit, (which is abſence indeede) haue no ſuch ioy in the vnities and ſocieties of our holy Brethren.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26420:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>Whereby wee euen hazard the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our Fathers bleſsing: who loueth to call vs, and to ſee vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, and then, and there to bleſſe vs; as <hi>Iacob,</hi> his' children:<note place="margin">Gen. 49, 1, 2</note> whome hee called togither, and then hee bleſſed them. For this is a promiſe to the plurall number, not ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely giuen vnto the ſingular: <hi>VVhere two or three are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in my name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 18.20</note> 
               <hi>there am I in the middest of them.</hi> And in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thirtie and third <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 133</note> 
               <hi>Beholde</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>howe good and pleaſant a thing it is brethren, to dwell togither in vnitie. It is like the precious Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vppon the heade, that ranne downe vnto the bearde; euen vnto Aarons beard, and went downe to the skirtes of his cloathing: Like as the dewe of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which fell vpon the Hill of Sion.</hi> And why ſo precious? and why ſo pleaſaunt? The reaſon is added:<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> 
               <hi>For there</hi> (this worde hee vſeth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26420:50"/>and as we ſay, emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callie) <hi>there,</hi> as if hee ſayde, <hi>there,</hi> and not elſe-where, as there, <hi>The Lord promiſeth his bleſsing, and life for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Balaam</hi> beguiled with the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Iude ver. 11 Num. 22, 13</note> woulde haue curſed the righteous. And yet hee cryeth out: <hi>Let my ſoule die the death of the iust;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 23, 10</note> 
               <hi>and let my latter ende bee like vnto theirs.</hi> All woulde die the death of the brethren; and manie profeſſe the faith of brethren: but all will not liue the life of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for the life of the brethren is their loue, which dieth not, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth euer.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13, 13</note> As <hi>Paule</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth faith, hope, and loue, euen theſe three. But the chiefest of theſe is loue.</hi> For it abydeth nowe, and euer. Whereupon Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> concludeth thus, (and with this I conclude al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.) <hi>By this wee knowe that we are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from death to life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.14</note> 
               <hi>becauſe wee loue
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26420:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>the brethren.</hi> For wee and our loue muſt liue togither.</p>
            <p>The God of peace, and loue, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe this loue, and knowledge in vs, and preſent vs blameleſſe in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt: to whom be prayſe for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
